<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-05-25T06:38:18-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/</id><title type="html">Happy &amp;amp; Productive</title><subtitle>This the personal blog of Sebastian Apel. I write about stuff that interests me. Currently that is being happy &amp; productive.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to Lay the Foundation for an Awesome Day</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/foundation-of-an-awesome-day" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Lay the Foundation for an Awesome Day" /><published>2018-05-24T03:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T03:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/foundation-of-an-awesome-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/foundation-of-an-awesome-day">&lt;p&gt;In my last posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/2GJv0ha&quot;&gt;habit formation&lt;/a&gt;, I have mentioned the Stanford University psychologist BJ Fogg. Another gold nugget I have gotten from him is his suggestion for an early morning habit that can lay the foundation for an awesome day. He calls it the MauiHabit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suggestion is to create the following habit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When&lt;/strong&gt; I get out of my bed, and &lt;strong&gt;my feet touch the ground,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
I will &lt;strong&gt;say to myself ‘Today is going to be an awesome day’.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I can understand if you think “Really? That’s it?”. I would have thought the same. But: I have tried his suggestion for the last couple of days: I was easy to do, it has put a smile on my face. That for itself could be enough, but on top of that, I have had a couple of awesome days this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I am not asking you to believe me. I am asking you to believe your own experience. Try this for a couple of days - and let me know how it works for you via Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In my last posts on habit formation, I have mentioned the Stanford University psychologist BJ Fogg. Another gold nugget I have gotten from him is his suggestion for an early morning habit that can lay the foundation for an awesome day. He calls it the MauiHabit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 words on … making habit formation more successful</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/making-habit-formation-more-successful" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 words on … making habit formation more successful" /><published>2018-05-24T03:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T03:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/100-words-on-raising-the-bar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/making-habit-formation-more-successful">&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I was talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/2GJv0ha&quot;&gt;making it easy to start&lt;/a&gt;: By making it so simple you cannot fail — and giving yourself permission to suck because it is highly likely that you will do so in the beginning. For me, the bar is currently: Publish 100 words every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One feedback I have received was: “Great, now that you have done 100 words — set the bar to 200 tomorrow.” But I am not going to raise the bar. At least not for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is based on BJ Foggs recommendation: &lt;strong&gt;“Easy” is key for establishing new habits&lt;/strong&gt;. Part of my objective is to set up a habit where I do this regularly. And to establish a behavior as a habit, it is necessary to do the behavior in the first place — and then be able to feel a sense of accomplishment after I have done the desired behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about publishing 100 words now, I immediately get the feeling: I can do this. That’s easy. Which actually makes me want to do the publishing, because I know I will feel great afterwards. On the other hand, if I would raise the bar, I felt myself unsure if I reach my goal — and as a consequence I was not as motivated to get started in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I will keep the bar at 100 words for now. And maybe raise the bar when I get to the point where I think “100 words is too boring”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d be interested if you have made a similar experience. Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In the last post, I was talking about making it easy to start: By making it so simple you cannot fail — and giving yourself permission to suck because it is highly likely that you will do so in the beginning. For me, the bar is currently: Publish 100 words every day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 words on … overcoming resistance to start publishing</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/overcoming-resistance-to-start" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 words on … overcoming resistance to start publishing" /><published>2018-05-23T03:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-23T03:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/100-words-on-overcoming-resistance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/overcoming-resistance-to-start">&lt;p&gt;I have been struggling with my objective to start publishing content on the Internet now for a while. I’ve tried a lot of things: Setting up habits to write every morning, reading a lot on how to do things. But in the end, I have not been able to establish something regular, much less publish ANYTHING.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I have listened to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/il-2a1UYb0&quot;&gt;podcast with BJ Fogg and David Kadavy&lt;/a&gt;: They were talking about how to make it &lt;strong&gt;simple enough&lt;/strong&gt; to just do it. And David said that he gave himself &lt;strong&gt;permission to suck&lt;/strong&gt;. So, I am resetting my bar to just publish 100 words for now. Without any wanting it to be great, awesome, new, innovative, value-adding. Just starting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because it is the only way to learn and get better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have been struggling with my objective to start publishing content on the Internet now for a while. I’ve tried a lot of things: Setting up habits to write every morning, reading a lot on how to do things. But in the end, I have not been able to establish something regular, much less publish ANYTHING.</summary></entry></feed>