<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-12T04:23:24-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/</id><title type="html">Happy &amp;amp; Productive</title><subtitle>This the blog of Sebastian Apel. I write about stuff that interests me. Currently that is being happy &amp; productive.</subtitle><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><entry><title type="html">Why Your Todo-List Makes You Unhappy &amp;amp; Frustrated (and What To Do About It)</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/why-your-todo-list-makes-you-unhappy-and-frustrated-and-what-to-do-about-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Your Todo-List Makes You Unhappy &amp; Frustrated (and What To Do About It)" /><published>2018-08-29T01:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-08-29T01:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/why-your-todo-list-makes-you-unhappy-and-frustrated-and-what-to-do-about-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/why-your-todo-list-makes-you-unhappy-and-frustrated-and-what-to-do-about-it.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;conventional-wisdom-takes-todo-lists-for-granted&quot;&gt;Conventional wisdom takes Todo-Lists for granted&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series of articles on “Self Management” on the
intersection of “Happyness &amp;amp; Productivity”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo-Lists have been with me for most of my professional life. I have taken them
for granted. I have believed “that’s how professionals &amp;amp; high achievers do it”.
(Oh, yes, and keeping all the stuff I want to do in my
head does not work either. So, writing it down is the way to go, right?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this was reinforced by “conventional wisdom”. Blogs write about Todo-Lists.
There are apps who help you to “digitize” your Todo-List. So who am I to doubt
the mighty wisdom of the Todo-List? Apparently that’s what you need when
you want to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-todo-list-will-help-me-to-be-happy-right&quot;&gt;The Todo-List will help me to be happy, right?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the underlying (not really explicit) belief (or maybe it’s better to call
it “hope”) was: Once I have achieved, then I will be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Todo-List was supposed to help me do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But happy did not come. Instead, unhappy &amp;amp; frustrated &amp;amp; overwhelmed came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: It cannot be the Todo-List, right? It must be myself who is doing it
wrong… I’m not achieving enough. No wonder I’m not happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what I believed for a long time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-more-closely&quot;&gt;Looking more closely&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know where the courage came from, but recently I find myself looking
at things I have taken “for granted” in a new way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I started to observe, and I realized the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the end of the day, I often was unhappy and felt I did not make any progress. Especially if I looked at all the stuff that I did not manage to get into the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And another observation was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When I tick an item “off” my todo list, then I automatically have to look at all the items that are NOT ticked yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trying-something-else&quot;&gt;Trying something else&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I decided to do something else at the end of each day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now writing an entry into my “Achievement and Reflection” journal
(basically a text document that I add to at the end).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reflect on the following four questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I create and/or ship and/or achieve today?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did I learn today?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do I want to repeat in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do I want to do differently in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;am-amazing-improvement&quot;&gt;Am amazing improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have abandoned the “classical” Todo-List for the sake of a this
end-of-day ritual, a “backlog” and “the pull principle”. I use the
“backlog” and “the pull principle” in the morning (you will find more
on those in follow-up posts), and the “Achievement and Reflection” journal
in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this has made a huge difference. I can now look at the day more
objectively and go home happy :-)  This then helps me to rest and relax
better, which in turn improves my happiness and effectiveness the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part for me was to establish the habit - and I will go more
into details in another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-you-want-to-read-more&quot;&gt;Do you want to read more?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is based on insights I had during my current project. That project
focuses on developing a framework that helps people to become more
“Happy &amp;amp; Productive”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button is-success&quot; href=&quot;/lp/discover-a-great-way-to-be-happy-and-productive.html&quot;&gt;
Tell me more about the framework!
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also going to write more articles on the topic. If you want to get
notified when I publish new content, you are invited to subscribe to
my email list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button is-success&quot; href=&quot;#newsletter-subscription&quot;&gt;
I want to stay updated!
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-author&quot;&gt;About the author&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Apel is an experienced Entrepreneur with extensive experience in
strategy &amp;amp; innovation. During his time as a Strategy Consultant, Sebastian
has supported major companies in becoming more innovative and agile. Sebastian
is a certified coach for the Lean Startup methodology, as well as a
certified consultant for agile development. His current mission is to help
other people be more happy &amp;amp; productive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">Conventional wisdom puts the Todo-List on a pedestal. I have done so, too - for a long time. But recently, I have realised that the tool that was supposed to help me bring happiness actually brings frustration &amp; overwhelm instead. And I have found a suprisingly effective alternative.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/design-desk-display-313690.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Think Traditional Planning Kills Motivation</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/traditional-planning-kills-motivation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Think Traditional Planning Kills Motivation" /><published>2018-08-17T04:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-08-17T04:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/traditional-planning-kills-motivation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/traditional-planning-kills-motivation.html">&lt;p&gt;“Where’s your 90 day plan that you commit to?” I was asked yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I had said that I am going to bring a plan.
But I did not. I did something else. Did not plan. I did not want to commit. But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, in the end, I did not want to feel like failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if I did not meet my goal, or plan, at the “committed upon” point in time - what would that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While thinking about this, I realized that I hestitated because it was
totally unclear what I would commit to. So, I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-i-think-i-am-right&quot;&gt;And I think I am right&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why: I simply cannot “estimate” correctly when I am going to be “done”. First thing is: “Done” needs to be defined. Then: the question of “when are you going to reach ‘done’” depends on several factors that influence “time of completion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of the factors from the top of my head. Let’s illustrate this by “laying a brick wall that is 1m high and 20m long”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Estimated) amount of work: to reach “done”, a certain amount of work needs to be “worked”. The unit of work takes a certain amount of time. Let’s estimate 1m width of a brick wall 1m high takes 3 hours to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Estimated) amount of “capacity to do work”: Well, if I have only 1hr during week days (because my day job is something else) and on the weekend I have 3,5hrs on both days, then I have a “capacity” of 5&lt;em&gt;1+2&lt;/em&gt;3,5 = 12hrs per week. That’s 4m of brick wall per week, of 5 weeks for 20m of brick wall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is before unexpected stuff happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-unexpected-stuff-happens&quot;&gt;But unexpected stuff happens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guy who is supposed to bring the bricks and mortar every week has a problem with the upstream delivery of mortar. Two weeks delay. My child gets sick, and therefore I cannot work on Friday and the weekend. Another week delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s 8 weeks instead of a 5 weeks. Great. And since I have committed to 5 weeks, my “accountability partner” (aka boss) will be asking: What’s happening? (”Are you not working hard enough?”, “Are you not good enough?”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list of “reasons” for the “delay” feels like an excuse. Even if I document every reason for a delay, the next round if discussion goes like (”Everybody knows that stuff happens - you should have planned for that in the first place” - and I hear “You are not good enough to plan”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes the process even more complicated is the fact that I want to do stuff I have never done before. So, how good are my estimates going to be? Very likely: very far from reality. So, it’s even more likely that I am “off target”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More likely I have the “discussion”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, what happens, if there is stuff on my list that I do not control? I.e. where there is not 100% probability of success? I do not know if the customer signs up. So, how can I commit to having 10 customers even I am not even sure if my offer is valuable enough so I get one person to buy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even more likely to have “the discussion”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s try and look at it from a perspective of “what’s the stuff that I (directly) control?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-my-own&quot;&gt;Time (my own)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can control the amount of time I invest (within limits, of course)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In that time, I can control what I work on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In that time, I can try to control how “focused” I work on the task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In that time, I can try to control how “effectively” I work on the task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money&quot;&gt;Money&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can “control” the amount of money I invest (within limits)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can control what I use the money for (until it’s gone)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can decide if I do it myself or if I get someone else to do it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources-that-i-do-not-control-directly&quot;&gt;Resources that I do not control directly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There also might be resources that are indirectly available to me. Those are mentioned in the book “A beautiful constraint” (chapter 5). But I am not going to go into detail here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-would-could-i-commit-to&quot;&gt;So, would could I commit to?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could commit to the things that are under my direct control. That includes the time and the money I am going to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I commit to budget for time &amp;amp; money, the next most important “lever” is the question of “what do I need/want to do next”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that stage, the best “input” is probably someone who has walked the path before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that of other people who say: Why do you think you need that? What would happen, if you tried this instead of that? I think there might be a shortcut here - have you thought about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s the discussion I want to have.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">I have an aversion towards traditional planning. And I have come to believe: rightfully so. Because it kills motivation. In this post, I explore an alternative, that I think is more effective.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why ‘Impact Theory’ is like a soft drink: An open letter to Tom Bilyeu</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/an-open-letter-to-Tom-Bilyeu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why 'Impact Theory' is like a soft drink: An open letter to Tom Bilyeu" /><published>2018-07-06T04:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-07-06T04:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/an-open-letter-to-Tom-Bilyeu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/an-open-letter-to-Tom-Bilyeu.html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Tom Bilyeu,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first say: Thank you for your show. This morning, I’ve literally had tears in my eyes because
I felt deeply thankful for the ideas that I encounter in your show. I am thankful, because you give me an
opportunity to glimpse into great minds that I otherwise don’t have access to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning, it was the interview with Naveen Jain and his thoughts on profits that were very
insightful. When I listened to the “After Impact” you were talking about the fact that it find the following fact “so distressing” (starting around 24:15) about “making people thirsty”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You explicitely “I am not making people thirsty. But if you are thirsty, come to me, I have a solution for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be very clear and frank: Tom Bilyeu, you currently DO NOT HAVE a solution. Or, if you have one, you are failing miserably at teaching or showing that solution. If your mission is to help people CHANGE their mindset, then you are falling short. Way short. I would even contradict your statement and say: Currently, ALL you do is making people thirsty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll go even further and say: you leave them thirsty, very similar to many speakers in the “mindset” arena (like Tony Robbins and others). Your “solution” currently is like a soft drink: you only get more thirsty by drinking the stuff…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you my perspective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How can you expect that passively “consuming” a 1hr show changes people deeply enough that they “go on and read 100 books?”  If “mindset change” was as easy as watching or reading “information about other people’s beliefs”, then we would have A LOT MORE billionaires out there. So, you need to “DO THE WORK”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am ready to do the work. In fact, that’s incorrect. I HAVE BEEN DOING SOME KIND OF WORK FOR YEARS. For years and years I’ve worked on changing my trajectory towards Entrepreneurship, Happiness and Health in my life. Basically since I encountered Tony Robbins in 2004.  I’ve got bookshelves full of books on the topic. I’ve read them. I listen to podcasts. Daily. I watch the Youtube channels. Daily. And it’s DEEPLY frustrating to see that my progress is slow, painfully slow. And let me assure you: It’s not because I haven’t worked hard. For years, I’ve slept 6hrs or less. I’ve worked 9-11pm. It’s not because I am not intellectually curious - I am. I don’t have a freakin televison. I rarely read the news any more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can’t hear the freakin “Work till you drop” advice any more. The research on is abundantly clear: If you neglect sleep, you HURT YOURSELF. Not enough sleep makes people dumb, fat, unhappy and dead.  So I’ve promised myself to get enough sleep from now on. I have a family which I am grateful for. To be honest: My family is I am most grateful for in my life. For years, I’ve prioritized work over my family. I’ve stopped doing that, because it just does not make sense to me any more: If I don’t spend time with my children - how are they supposed to be inspired by me? How am I supposed to help them develop a great mindset? How are my children supposed to develop a feeling of “I am important” if the implicit message they are getting all the freaking time is “Something else (work, self improvement) is more important than you are”?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My problems are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the RIGHT work I need to do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I identify the LIMITING BELIEFS in my mindset?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I replace the LIMITING BELIEF with a BETTER BELIEF?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What should I TRAIN on a daily basis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me use a metaphor to describe what I am thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently you are saying “I don’t get it - I’ve shown people videos about great Triathletes
who are killing it in the Ironman competition. I can see how fired up they are. With those triathletes,
I talk about how they think about Triathlon, and how they mentally manage the challeges. We talk what those Athletes THINK when their muscles hurt after swimming and cycling. But people are just not executing against that…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that’s because the audience has tried to adopt the MINDSET and they have realized that they still are not a top athlete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom, I need a “training plan”. I need somebody to tell me: In week 1, train swimming on Monday and Thursdays, running on Tuesdays, cycling on Saturdays. Take the other days off, because your body needs to recover. In week 2 do this. In week 3, do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That might be a SOLUTION that works for me. Otherwise, all the content is just like soft drinks: They make me more thirsty.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">I am deeply thankful for Tom Bilyeu and his show Impact Theory. But I also think that Tom Bilyeu falls short in accomplishing the mission he has set out to do. He is not solving the problem he wants to solve. It does not help people to achieve what they want to achieve - it just dangles the carrot in front of people's face without telling people how to get it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Four things you need to know to use the “Lean Startup” safely</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/what-you-need-to-know-to-use-lean-startup-safely.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Four things you need to know to use the “Lean Startup” safely" /><published>2018-07-04T06:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-07-04T06:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/what-you-need-to-know-to-use-lean-startup-safely</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/what-you-need-to-know-to-use-lean-startup-safely.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;management-summary&quot;&gt;Management Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Lean Startup” methodology is one of the State-of-the-Art methodologies
for building successful companies at the current stage.
But, it is no silver bullet, and if you are not careful, it can hurt you.
Badly. Painfully. In this article, I tell you where I think a few of the
pitfalls are and I will give you my thoughts on what you can do to avoid the
pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lean Startup methodology has two major building blocks:
The &lt;strong&gt;“Build/Measure/Learn”&lt;/strong&gt; cycle, and the &lt;strong&gt;“Minimum Viable Product”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, both of these concepts have major strengths, this is why the “Lean
Startup Methodolgy” was so successful. But they both have major
weaknesses. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mvp--buildmeasurelearn-considered-harmful&quot;&gt;MVP &amp;amp; Build/Measure/Learn considered harmful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Build/Measure/Learn cycle is part of Lean Startup to address the problem
that “we cannot know everything in advance”. I agree that the problem
exists. Especially at the beginning of a new business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the methodology suggests to “build an MVP, show the customer, learn
from the data”. If the unexperienced starting Entrepreneur now follows the
receipe, the will naturally this “OK, the method says I have to build an
MVP, so let’s go and build an MVP.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-doubts-regarding-the-methodology&quot;&gt;First doubts regarding the methodology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I had a discussion with an experienced professional in the retail industry,
he said: “Look, Sebastian, I’ve not read the book ‘Lean Startup’. But I find it
hard to believe that the book does not talk about ‘research’ at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went back and double checked. And: No, there’s no notion of research in
Eric Ries’ book “Lean Startup”. It even explicitly makes a case against it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;If Zappos had relied on existing market research, it could have asked what
customers thought they wanted. By building a product instead the company learned
much more…&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in a nutshell, Entrepreneurs are explicitly advised to build instead of
doing research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-first-effort-to-mitigate-this-problem&quot;&gt;A first effort to mitigate this problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Blank, one of the “founding fathers” of the Lean Startup methodology also
has written against this focus on “building in his post &lt;a href=&quot;“https://steveblank.com/2015/05/06/build-measure-learn-throw-things-against-the-wall-and-see-if-they-work/”&quot;&gt;“Why Build, Measure, Learn – isn’t just throwing things against the wall to see if they work – the Minimal Viable Product”&lt;/a&gt;: In his post, he acknowledes that the focus on
“build” and “ideas” is leading into the wrong direction. He suggests to
focus on “hypotheses” and “experiments” about the “Business Model” instead.
He goes on mention the &lt;strong&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/strong&gt; as a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-model-canvas-considered-harmful&quot;&gt;Business Model Canvas considered harmful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://strategyzer.com/canvas/business-model-canvas&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was
co-created by Alexander Osterwalder.  It’s main value lies in having
the “business model” on one page. For this, it has 9 sections
that relect core aspects of any business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has reached widespread adoption, because of it’s ability to “reduce”
long business plan documents to their essentials and thus facilitate a better
discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other people have called the Business Model Canvas the &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;https://www.alexandercowan.com/business-model-canvas-templates/#What_if_I_want_more_structure_to_work_through_this&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“20 minute business
plan”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it’s possible to fill Business Model Canvas created in 20 minutes. And
that’s what’s encouraged in most of the courses I’ve seen: You are asked
to create a “complete” canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, no problem, it only takes 20 minutes. After discussing a couple of
canvases with a coach, you will also get “good” at filling them: they
will not have any “obvious” contradictions any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You Business Model now “works” (in theory). But the problem is: The
content on the Canvas still is from “Guessland”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you follow the methodology, your job now is to “build”. But: Have you
reduced the “risk”? No, probably not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if you build a product now? Your likelihood of “missing” the
customer needs are high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have suggested “improved versions” of the canvas - for example
Ash Maurya with his “Lean Canvas”. It
even claims to be “&lt;a href=&quot;https://leanstack.com/leancanvas&quot;&gt;optimized for Lean Startup&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it has the same fundamental weaknesses: While it shows
“all the important things of a business at a glance”, and can be created
in “less than 20 minutes”, the Canvas at the same time
does not help you to &lt;strong&gt;“de-risk”&lt;/strong&gt; your major risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-getting-out-of-the-building-and-customer-interviews&quot;&gt;What about “Getting out of the building” and “Customer Interviews”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, other thought leaders in the “Lean Startup” ecosphere have talked
about “research”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book “The Startup Owners Manual”, Steve Blank explicitely talks about
“getting out of the building” and doing “customer discovery”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ash Maurya even has an “interview script” that he offers entrepreneurs as
a helpful guide to talk to the customer before “building”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: The “customer interview” approach is also problematic,
because interviews are scary for many people and hard to do “correctly”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;you may end up hearing what you want to hear (called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer-expectancy_effect&quot;&gt;“Observer
      Expectancy Effect”&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and the pure fact that you are interviewing can change the behaviour of
  the interview partners (an effect well known in Social Sciences called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawthorne_effect&quot;&gt;“Hawthorne effect”&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree, this is better then “building an MVP” without any customer interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: One of the main observations of this approach is: it is still very costly.
Ash Maurya suggests to plan about 3 months (calendar) time for
doing Customer Interviews, with ideally two people at the interview, albeit
part time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three major problems with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It still is a major investment. 3 months, two people, 50 interviews. If you
assume 3 hours per interview (1 hr commute, 1 hr interview, 1 hr documentation),
thats already 2 people x 50 interviews x 3 hours = 300 hours = 37,5 work day
equivalents + 2,5 days preparation &amp;amp; sythesis x 500 USD per day = 20k USD. Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It limits the “feedback loop cycle time” to about 3 months. Ouch again. That’s
long, especially if you remind yourself: Your assumptions are probably wrong
anyway, because you were guessing when you filled out the Canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do you do after you have falsified your initial assumptions?  Given
the likelihood your assumptions are wrong, that’s the major question.
My observation is: if people are lucky, they discover a problem worth solving
on the way and start focusing on that problem - that’s the group that might
become “successful”, if they get the a lot of things right.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I look at it that way, it does not make much sense to me: What
good is a method that creates a false sense of reliability, that costs me
3 months, at least 20k USD, and still hinges on “luck” to find something
that might work on the way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;that-was-a-lot---what-are-the-4-things-i-need-to-remember&quot;&gt;That was a lot - what are the 4 things I need to remember?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the summary of my observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lean Startup has a strong bias towards “building” an MVP very early
 in the process. But “building” is expensive, both in terms of (calendar)
 time-to-learning, as well as money and opportunity cost (cost-per-learning).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The suggested “remedy” of using the Business Model Canvas may help to
 remove the obvious logic flaws in the business modell - but you
 are still largely “guessing”. Starting to “build” on that foundation is
 still as expensive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The augmentation of Lean Startup with “customer interviews” has reduced
 monetary cost (somewhat), but is still “expensive” regarding (calendar)
 “time-to-learning”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The success probability of the approach still “hinges” largely on
 gut feeling of the Entrepreneur and a component of “luck” and “finding” a
 problem worth solving for the customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ok-what-should-i-do&quot;&gt;OK, what should I do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a great question. My advise is: instead of focusing on “building an MVP”
ask yourself “What is the fastest way to achieve the learning I am looking for?”.
You can learn a lot about your (potential) clients through desk research. use
those opportunities. And then, as a next step, start “building”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the next weeks and months, I am going to work on a framework
that provides a more structured approach to that question. I am going to
focus on the major KPIs of “time-to-learning” and “cost-per-learning”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be part of that journey subscribe to my email list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-author&quot;&gt;About the author&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Apel is an experienced Entrepreneur with extensive experience in
strategy &amp;amp; innovation. During his time as a Strategy Consultant, Sebastian
has supported major companies in becoming more innovative and agile. Sebastian
is a certified coach for the Lean Startup methodology, as well as a
certifed consultant for agile development. His current mission is to improve
the likelihoods of Entrepreneurial success, both for companies as well as
founders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eric Ries (2011), The Lean Startup: How Today’s Entrepreneurs Use Continuous Innovation to Create Radically Successful Businesses &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.de/dp/0307887898?ref=nosim&amp;amp;tag=471108152102-21&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steve Blank, Bob Dorf (2012), The Startup Owner’s Manual: The Step-By-Step Guide for Building a Great Company &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.de/dp/0984999302?ref=nosim&amp;amp;tag=471108152102-21&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ash Maurya (2012), Running Lean: Iterate from Plan A to a Plan That Works (Lean Series) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.de/dp/1449305172?ref=nosim&amp;amp;tag=471108152102-21&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">The “Lean Startup” methodology is one of the State-of-the-Art methodologies for building successful companies at the current stage. But, it is no silver bullet, and if you are not careful, it can hurt you. Badly. Painfully. In this article, I tell you where I think a few of the pitfalls are and I will give you my thoughts on what you can do to avoid the pitfalls.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/teddy-teddy-bear-association-ill-42230.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to mentally prepare when you want to become an Entrepreneur</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/how-to-mentally-prepare-when-you-want-to-become-an-entrepreneur.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to mentally prepare when you want to become an Entrepreneur" /><published>2018-06-29T06:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-29T06:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/how-to-mentally-prepare-when-you-want-to-become-an-entrepreneur</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/how-to-mentally-prepare-when-you-want-to-become-an-entrepreneur.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/resized/800/teddy-teddy-bear-association-ill-42230.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;becoming-an-entrepreneur-is-dangerous-for-your-mental-health&quot;&gt;Becoming an Entrepreneur is dangerous for your mental health&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant number of people have the dream to become an Entrepreneur.
Some of the dreamers embark on that journey. But: only very few make it.
So far, so known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less known, but even more alarming is that a larger amout of Entrepreneurs
seem to hurt themselves
on the journey.  Chris Myers has written on Forbes, that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/chrismyers/2018/01/17/three-things-every-entrepreneur-needs-to-remember-when-dealing-with-depression/#3de5afa0366c&quot;&gt;30% of Entrepreuners
are suffering from depression, while only 7% of the general population has that problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been asking myself: why is that the case?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;psychology-to-the-rescue&quot;&gt;Psychology to the rescue&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look at this through the lens of Martin Seligmann’s theory of &lt;a href=&quot;https://positivepsychologyprogram.com/learned-helplessness-seligman-theory-depression-cure/&quot;&gt;“Depression and Learned
Helplessness”&lt;/a&gt;, the model states that a person will develop depression[2], when&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the person believes that the desired outcomes are improbable,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or he/she believes that an undesired outcome is probable,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and the person believes that she cannot do anything to change that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Entrepreneurship. I can understand every Entrepreneur who get’s the
feeling of “I can’t reach my desired outcome” after pouring heart and soul
into a project that does not take off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;carol-dweck-again&quot;&gt;Carol Dweck, again&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It get’s even more interesting when you look at Carol Dweck’s 1975 study “The
role of expectations and attributions in the alleviation of learned
helplessness”[3].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, she had participants work on problems. Some of the participants
were allowed to “always be successful” by lowering the standard below their
level of performance (SO=Success Only).
Others were exposed to “failure” by setting the bar above
their performance &lt;em&gt;on purpose&lt;/em&gt;. In addition to communicating the failure,
the researchers also offered an explanation to the participants: “You should
have tried harder.” (AR=Attribution Retraining).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, during a test phase, the subjects were exposed to a “real” test scenario.
In the “real” test scenario, both groups got the same procedure. The procedure
contained  “preplanned” failure scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And (not really surprising): Those subjects in the AR group who had “practiced”
failure where able to deal with the failure scenario and improve their performance.
The group that was only used to be “successful” could not handle failure very
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;interesting-but-what-does-this-have-to-do-with-learning-entrepreneurship&quot;&gt;Interesting, but what does this have to do with learning Entrepreneurship?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, if your are used to be successful in whatever you have done before: Brace
for impact. On the road to Entrepreneurship, stuff will not work as you want
it to. And if you are not used to that, the fact that something is not working
according to plan will have a detrimental effect on your performance. Not really
a “virtuous circle”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the following mindshift tremendously important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try to build your self esteem around “showing up”, “trying” and “learning”.
A good sentence for that might be “I am the kind of person that …”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check if curiosity helps: A sentence like “I wonder what happens if I try X”
can do wonders&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Practice” failure every day: Do hard stuff that you can not yet do - and
train yourself to deal with the thoughts and emotions that come up then.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are you preparing yourself for the journey? Send me an email, I’m curious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chris Myers (2018), Three Things Every Entrepreneur Needs To Remember When Dealing With Depression &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/chrismyers/2018/01/17/three-things-every-entrepreneur-needs-to-remember-when-dealing-with-depression/#3de5afa0366c&quot;&gt;https://www.forbes.com/sites/chrismyers/2018/01/17/three-things-every-entrepreneur-needs-to-remember-when-dealing-with-depression/#3de5afa0366c&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Courtney Ackerman (2018), Learned Helplessness: Seligman’s Theory of Depression (+ Cure), retrieved from  &lt;a href=&quot;https://positivepsychologyprogram.com/learned-helplessness-seligman-theory-depression-cure/&quot;&gt;https://positivepsychologyprogram.com/learned-helplessness-seligman-theory-depression-cure/)&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dweck, Carol (1975). The role of expectations and attributions in the alleviation of learned helplessness, Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 31, 674-685, retrieved from  &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/Stuff/dw1975_attributions.pdf&quot;&gt;http://slatestarcodex.com/Stuff/dw1975_attributions.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">Entrepreneurship is tough: The percentage of Entrepreneurs that suffer from depression is more then 4 times higher than the same percentage in the normal population. The question is: What do you do to prepare?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/teddy-teddy-bear-association-ill-42230.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I stopped drinking Bulletproof Coffee</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/why-i-stopped-drinking-bulletproof-coffee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I stopped drinking Bulletproof Coffee" /><published>2018-06-26T06:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-26T06:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/why-i-stopped-drinking-bulletproof-coffee</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/why-i-stopped-drinking-bulletproof-coffee.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to try things. When I read about Dave Asprey’s Bulletproof Coffee, it sounded awesome: “Boost your Energy and Brain Function”, “Suppress Hunger, Loose Weight, Think Faster…”. Man, who would not want that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a curious guy, I’ve tried it for about 6 weeks during the weekdays. I definitely had some of the benefits: I was not hungry until lunch, I could concentrate in the mornings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all things worked as advertised: I did not loose weight, au contraire, I gained some weight. And, after a while, I started to feel worse and worse. Tired in the afternoons. A little nauseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I asked myself: what’s wrong here? I started thinking and reseaching a bit - and you find my results below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before that, let’s have a quick look at the reciepe again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bulletproof Coffee &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.bulletproof.com/how-to-make-your-coffee-bulletproof-and-your-morning-too/&quot;&gt;consists of the following ingredients&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coffee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1-2 tablespoons of Unsalted Butter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1-2 tablespoons of MCT Oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weight-reduction&quot;&gt;Weight Reduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at weight reduction first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;your Bulletproof Coffee will be high caloric, because of the high fat content:
if you stick to the 1 tablespoon for butter &amp;amp; oil, that’s about 230 kcal.
If you use 2 tablespoons for both, that’s 460 kcal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sedentary person “burns” about 2000 kcal per day. If you want to loose weight,
you need to be below that. There’s the rule of thumb, that you need to have
a 500 kcal daily caloric deficit to loose 1lb of body fat in a week &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/calories-in-a-pound-of-fat&quot;&gt;(although
	people also say that’s not true)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for our example, let’s stick to that and assume a 1500 kcal per day “target”.
This means, after your bulletproof coffee, you have used 15-30% of your daily
caloric “allowance” right after you finished drinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nutrient-intake&quot;&gt;Nutrient Intake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other observation is: with those calories, you have not had ANY vitamins,
ANY minerals, and no protein. This is similar for soft drinks - only that
those calories are called “empty calories” in the case for soft drinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even the marketing is similar: one famous soft drink was announced as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coca-colacompany.com/stories/the-first-ad-for-cocacola&quot;&gt;“Delicious! Refreshing! Exhilirating! Invigorating!”&lt;/a&gt;
in it’s first ad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to nutrient intake: in order to get all the nutrients you need,
this means you have to get the nutrients from the rest of your meals that day.
Which is already hard enough without replacing one whole meal with empty calories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, let’s have a look at Potassium intake. Potassium is present in all
body tissues and is required for normal cell function. It is an essential
nutrient, because the body cannot produce it itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Health Organisation
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK132453/&quot;&gt;recommends 3510 mg/day of Potassium for adults [1].&lt;/a&gt;
The Food and Nutrition Board (FNB) at the National Academies of Sciences,
Engineering, and Medicine even &lt;a href=&quot;https://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/Potassium-HealthProfessional/&quot;&gt;recommends 4700 mg/day [2].&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: this recommendation is already not reached, according to
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/Potassium-HealthProfessional/&quot;&gt;National Insititutes of Health [2]&lt;/a&gt;. They cite studies that suggest that the average potassium intake from foods
are around 3000mg of Potassium for males and 2300mg for females.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine what leaving out a whole meal means for your (probably already too
low) Potassium intake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal guess for myself is: I have not been been consuming more. Because
if you have a look at the symptoms of mild potassium deficiency (hypokalemia),
you will find: “Mild hypokalemia is characterized by constipation,
fatigue, muscle weakness, and malaise [2]”. Which describes how I felt pretty
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-personal-consequences&quot;&gt;My personal consequences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From those observations, my conclusions were pretty straight forward:
it’s probably a better idea to have healthy &lt;em&gt;food&lt;/em&gt; for breakfast and
use that meal to get the nutrients my body needs.
And this is what I have returned to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World Health Organisation (2012), Guideline: Potassium Intake for
Adults and Children, retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK132453/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK132453/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;National Institutes of Health, Office of Dietary Supplements, Potassium Fact Sheet for Health Professionals, retrieved from  &lt;a href=&quot;https://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/Potassium-HealthProfessional/&quot;&gt;https://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/Potassium-HealthProfessional/)&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">After trying Bulletproof Coffee for a while, I've returned to eating breakfast. One reason is that I did not get the benefits I was hoping for. After thinking and researching for a while, I've formed the opinion that it's a bad idea. Read the article to find out why...</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/beverage-breakfast-brewed-coffee-374885.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Not getting enough sleep hurts your mental performance</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/sleep-and-mental-performance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not getting enough sleep hurts your mental performance" /><published>2018-06-22T06:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-22T06:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/sleep-and-mental-performance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/sleep-and-mental-performance.html">&lt;p&gt;This is going to be one of several articles in which I am going to explore
what science has to say about &lt;a href=&quot;en/exploring-sleep-and-performance.html&quot;&gt;“Sleep and Human Performance”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each article, we are going to explore one scientific study that sheds light
on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question I have asked myself is “How does lack of sleep affect mental
performance?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the University of Turku have written a nice summary on
“Sleep deprivation: Impact on cognitive performance” [1]. One of the studies
they cite was done by the US Military in the Walter Reed Army
Institute of Research [2].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “too long, did not read” summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleeping less than 8 hours reduced the mental performance of the participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even a small reduction to 7 hours of sleep per night already hurt the cognitive performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was even worse when participants slept 5 hours or 3 hours per night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After 7 days of less than 8 hours of sleep, even 3 days of recovery
(8 hrs in bed) was &lt;em&gt;not enough&lt;/em&gt; to bring back the performance
to the level of the people who were not sleep restricted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, researchers of the Walter Reed Army Institute of Research have studied how sleeping less impacts cognitive function. As one measure for “cognitive function” they used the “Psychomotor vigilance task” where you need to press a button as soon as a light shows up on a screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They established a baseline by having people stay in bed for 8 hrs for 3 days, and then restricting sleep for 7 days, followed by a 3 day recovery period with again 8 hours sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the sleep restriction period, they had 4 groups with different amounts of time in bed: 9 hours, 7 hours, 5 hours, 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first group that had 9 hours sleep per night: Their performance did not change over the next 7 days.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For all other groups, the performance got worse and over the 7 days of sleep restriction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the recovery peroid, only the group that had had 3 hours of sleep “improved” again. But: They were still performing worse then the 5 hour group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paula Alhola and Päivi Polo-Kantola (2007), Sleep deprivation: Impact on cognitive performance, Journal of Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment, pp 553–567, retrieved from  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2656292/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2656292&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gregory Belenky, Nancy J. Wesensten, David R. Thorne, Maria L. Thomas,
Helen C. Sing, Daniel P. Redmond, Michael B. Russo, Thomas J. Balkin (2003),
Patterns of performance degradation and restoration during sleep
restriction and subsequent recovery: a sleep dose‐response study, Journal of
Sleep Research, retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1046/j.1365-2869.2003.00337.x&quot;&gt;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1046/j.1365-2869.2003.00337.x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">Honestly, the fact that your mental performance suffers when you do not get enough sleep is not surprising. What was surprising to me was the fact that this effect is already measurable after 7 hours of sleep.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Overcome Procrastination: Great Tips from a book by Neil Fiore</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/how-to-overcome-procrastination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Overcome Procrastination: Great Tips from a book by Neil Fiore" /><published>2018-06-19T06:30:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-19T06:30:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/overcoming-procrastination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/how-to-overcome-procrastination.html">&lt;p&gt;A question that I have read a lot is “How can I get disciplined and start doing what I have planned?”. I’ve read this in the context of studying, but also in the context of entrepreneurs who start out with a new idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will summarize Neil Fiore’s book “Overcoming Procrastination: Practice the Now Habit and Guilt-Free Play”. This book is very similar to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.de/dp/1585425524?ref=nosim&amp;amp;tag=471108152102-21&quot;&gt;his newer book “The Now Habit”&lt;/a&gt;, which might be easier to obtain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can definitely recommend reading this book - it brings a very different
perspective to the problem and shows very practical, implementable ways of
dealing with the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niel Fiore’s main hypothesis in this book is that procrastination &lt;strong&gt;is a mechanism
for coping with anxiety associated with starting or completing any task or
decision&lt;/strong&gt;. He explicitly states that his definition is different from the usual
world view of “procrastination is a problem of my personality”, and “I am not
trying hard enough” or “I am not disciplined enough”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3 major fear Neil Fiore identifies are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fear of being overwhelmed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fear of failure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fear of finishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His approach to dealing with procrastination is based on the goal of helping
the indiviual feeling safe and have positive relationship towards work and
producing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book shows the following levers for approaching procrastination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing your inner dialogue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes to your “work/life balance”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tools to deal with the 3 major fears&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dealing with (inevitable) setbacks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will pick my personal highlights from the first two categories, which are by no means
complete:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-changing-your-inner-dialogue&quot;&gt;1) Changing your inner dialogue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How you talk to yourself regarding the tasks you are procrastinating on has a
very strong influence on your personal well being and on the likelihood of
yourself working on those tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take the specific example. Imagine that you have to
“write a book summary”. I invite you to play along and try out how the
statements make you feel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negative self talk: “I have to write the book summary”: If I say this to myself,
I feel under pressure, like “I don’t want to, but I have to”. Neil Fiore
explains how this statement has a subtle undercurrent of victimhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggested approach: Remind yourself that you have the choice: You can do the
task - or accept the consequences. In this case: You can either choose to
live with the consequences of not writing the book summary - or you choose to
write it. It’s up to you. Once you have decided you do not live with the
consequences, make sure to use the more exact language of “I choose to written
the book summary”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other negative statements Neil Fiore discusses are “I must finish”, “This is
so big”, “I must be perfect”, “I don’t have time to play”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-change-your-worklife-balance&quot;&gt;2) Change your work/life balance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One “trap” you can fall into is following an “all work, no play” approach.
According to Neil Fiore, this backfires, because it will increase the likelihood
to procrastinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suggestes something counter-intuitive: In order to get yourself to work
on the things you want to work on, &lt;em&gt;schedule the ‘play’-activities&lt;/em&gt; first.
This means: When creating your weekly calendar, the first thing you should put
is the things you enjoy doing. And: you have to stick to those committments to
yourself. Work gets scheduled into the remaining time slots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Fiore calls this the “unschedule”, and he illustrates how this idea is based
on the principle of “reverse psychology” and how it makes you sitting down and
doing the work more likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said: I can definitely recommend this book. I think it brings deep
insight to the problem and has very implementable advice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">Many people struggeling with procrastination have the feeling that it is a character deficit. In his book &quot;Overcoming Procrastination&quot;, Dr. Neil Fiore explains why this is not the case - and has great tips of for overcoming the problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Hard Path of Getting from Self-Help Consumption to Implementing Real Change</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/getting-from-self-help-consumption-to-real-change.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hard Path of Getting from Self-Help Consumption to Implementing Real Change" /><published>2018-06-11T01:20:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-11T01:20:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/getting-from-self-help-consumption-to-real%20change</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/getting-from-self-help-consumption-to-real-change.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I read a post on reddit where somebody was saying: “Hey, I feel like I am a self help addict - I consume a lot of information from podcasts, blogs, (audio) books, but when it comes to implementation, then I either do not start in the first place, or I stop again soon after starting”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this person was wondering if anyone has had a similar experience, I could say: Yes, totally. I have consumed a lot of self help content, too. And I too got frustrated because I realized: I only translated a very limited amount of the information that I consumed into action. I also had the experience, that I would execute some things for a certain time, but then I quit those things again. The person was also talking about wanting to quit meditation… And I could relate to the meditation example: Been there, done that, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently experimenting with the following things (and I am actually quite happy with it currently):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mindset change: Reading Carol Dweck’s “Mindset” was actually an eyeopener for me: Before reading the book, I would have told you: “I sure have a growth mindset.” While reading the book, I realized: That’s not true, because I actually avoid the feeling of “I cannot do it (yet)”. And since this feeling is inherent in any kind of new behavior, it was blocking me from really doing to hard stuff (or expecting it to come easy to me). I’ve tried to counter this by giving myself “permission to suck (at least for a while)”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Habit formation: I try to set up “habits” to automate behavior I want to establish. The “tiny habits” approach was very helpful for me, I written about why in &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/2scpcrm&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Journaling: I’ve created a “journal template” for myself, basically a set of questions that I answer. The questions remind me of the “tiny habits” I am trying to establish, and they guide me through the thought process I wanted to use to reflect on the last 24 hrs, including what was good and what do I want do do differently in the next 24 hrs. After setting up the tiny habit of sitting down every morning [of each workday], I have been using this template for about 4 weeks now. It’s a lot easier for me to journal this way, because it “guides” me in areas where I have not yet set up the habits that I would like to have.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially the journaling habits is very helpful, because I recently started to ask myself a question from my journal template &lt;strong&gt;automatically&lt;/strong&gt;. Which was an amazing feeling. Because it made me realize: I can change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am curious if you have been at this place, too - and what has worked for you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">If you feel like you are consuming a lot of self help content without really implementing something on your side, then you can find a littble bit of solace in the fact that you are not alone. And if you are really frustrated with the fact, here are 3 things that have helped my to move forward.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Biggest Mistake You Can Make When Selecting an Email List Provider as a Starting Entrepreneur</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/biggest-mistake-when-selecting-email-list-providers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Biggest Mistake You Can Make When Selecting an Email List Provider as a Starting Entrepreneur" /><published>2018-06-07T01:20:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-07T01:20:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/biggest-mistake-when-selecting-email-list-providers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/en/biggest-mistake-when-selecting-email-list-providers.html">&lt;p&gt;Are you an entrepreneur who is just starting? A blogger who wants to grow an email list? And are you asking yourself “Which is the best email list prodiver for me to use”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hear you. I’ve been there. My thought process was: I want to build an email list. Everybody successful has one. That’s why I need an email list provider, too. And, logically, I was asking myself “Which is the best email list prodiver for me to use?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent time researching the options, ended up testing Mailjet, not being happy with the outcome, researched more options, tested Sendy, not being happy with the fact that it did not let me know if the outbound emails were really sent, tested CleverReach where I was not happy with the fact that they have a Google ReCaptcha in the form. Tried to test Newsletter2Go, where they are still validating my company details at the time of writing, which means I could not even test their functionality as of yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After looking at my notes on the time it took me, I thing it took me about 10 hrs of work to get where I am now. And my outcome is qualitatively not where I want it to be, so I can choose to invest more time of live with the mediocre status quo. Frustrating. Really frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: I’ve had an insight: I’ve been asking myself the wrong question. The right question is “Do I REALLY need an email list provider NOW?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my advice to you is: No, my friend, most likely not. I will probably need one. Later. But NOW, it’s very likely not required. I would even argue: It hurts you right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hurts you, because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will take you a lot of time to set the provider up (think 8+ hours)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You will most likely not be happy with the result (I was not with mine)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This will then frustrate you (I know I was)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which will raise the likelihood of you saying “WTF - this Entrepreneurship-Thing is not for me”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And on top, it takes away a great opportunity: The 1st hand experience of interacting with your potential customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My suggestion to you is: Do not use an email list provider. Implement something similar to my setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a signup form sends an email to yourself along the lines “Hi Sebastian, would you please add me to your email list?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the person to an email list in your email client&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write a freshly created email back to the person, thanking them for their interest, and start a conversation with them… Tell them “this is not a robot, it’s a real human”. Ask them what their biggest struggle is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know how this feels like? Use the form below :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sebastian Apel</name></author><summary type="html">Are you asking yourself: 'What's the best email provider for me to use?' Good for you! But: be aware of the biggest mistake you can make when selecting one as a starting Entrepreneur.</summary></entry></feed>