<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-08T06:31:06-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/</id><title type="html">Happy &amp;amp; Productive</title><subtitle>This the personal blog of Sebastian Apel. I write about stuff that interests me. Currently that is being happy &amp; productive.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Biggest Mistake You Can Make When Selecting an Email List Provider as a Starting Entrepreneur</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/biggest-mistake-when-selecting-email-list-providers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Biggest Mistake You Can Make When Selecting an Email List Provider as a Starting Entrepreneur" /><published>2018-06-07T01:20:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-07T01:20:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/biggest-mistake-when-selecting-email-list-providers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/biggest-mistake-when-selecting-email-list-providers">&lt;p&gt;Are you an entrepreneur who is just starting? A blogger who wants to grow an email list? And are you asking yourself “Which is the best email list prodiver for me to use”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hear you. I’ve been there. My thought process was: I want to build an email list. Everybody successful has one. That’s why I need an email list provider, too. And, logically, I was asking myself “Which is the best email list prodiver for me to use?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent time researching the options, ended up testing Mailjet, not being happy with the outcome, researched more options, tested Sendy, not being happy with the fact that it did not let me know if the outbound emails were really sent, tested CleverReach where I was not happy with the fact that they have a Google ReCaptcha in the form. Tried to test Newsletter2Go, where they are still validating my company details at the time of writing, which means I could not even test their functionality as of yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After looking at my notes on the time it took me, I thing it took me about 10 hrs of work to get where I am now. And my outcome is qualitatively not where I want it to be, so I can choose to invest more time of live with the mediocre status quo. Frustrating. Really frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: I’ve had an insight: I’ve been asking myself the wrong question. The right question is “Do I REALLY need an email list provider NOW?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my advice to you is: No, my friend, most likely not. I will probably need one. Later. But NOW, it’s very likely not required. I would even argue: It hurts you right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hurts you, because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will take you a lot of time to set the provider up (think 8+ hours)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You will most likely not be happy with the result (I was not with mine)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This will then frustrate you (I know I was)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which will raise the likelihood of you saying “WTF - this Entrepreneurship-Thing is not for me”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And on top, it takes away a great opportunity: The 1st hand experience of interacting with your potential customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My suggestion to you is: Do not use an email list provider. Implement something similar to my setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a signup form sends an email to yourself along the lines “Hi Sebastian, would you please add me to your email list?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the person to an email list in your email client&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write a freshly created email back to the person, thanking them for their interest, and start a conversation with them… Tell them “this is not a robot, it’s a real human”. Ask them what their biggest struggle is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know how this feels like? Use the form below :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Are you asking yourself: 'What's the best email provider for me to use?' Good for you! But: be aware of the biggest mistake you can make when selecting one as a starting Entrepreneur.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting back on the horse</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/what-to-do-after-you-failed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting back on the horse" /><published>2018-06-04T08:20:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T08:20:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/getting-back-on-the-horse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/what-to-do-after-you-failed">&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple four days, I’ve not been writing. There was a public
holiday, I was outside of my usual environment because I was travelling with
my family. I did not have a good topic to write about. Many reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I am very unhappy about that. I feel bad, because I have not
made any progress. So, what can you do in such a situation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way I can think of is derived from horseback riding: If you have fallen
of the horse, you need to get back it.  That’s basically it. Not a long story.
Nothing fancy. Just get back up and write your 100 words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you should act as your personal horseback riding teacher.
A good teacher will not shame you, because you have fallen of the horse.
He will help you understand why you have fallen off, and he will motivate you
to get back on the horse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a better approach anyway: I cannot change the last couple of days, but
I can make sure that today is different.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When starting a new habit, you will fail at some point in time. The question is: what are you going to do about it? Are you going to shame yourself? Or are you helping yourself to get back onto the horse?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Build Great Habits (pt 1)</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/how-to-build-great-habits-pt1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Build Great Habits (pt 1)" /><published>2018-05-29T03:35:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-29T03:35:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/how-to-build-great-habits-pt1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/how-to-build-great-habits-pt1">&lt;p&gt;In my last post, I promised to write more about how to create great habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-is-knowing-about-habits-helpful&quot;&gt;Why is knowing about habits helpful?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to look into habits, because I was struggeling to get myself to do things differently. I had tried the approach to “remind myself to do something”. That worked, but not very reliably: I would remind myself of the behaviour sometimes. But on a lot of days, I realized in the evening that I had forgotten what I wanted to do. And that was very frustrating. And not very effective. And energy consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, after reading “&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2J0qAnO&quot;&gt;The Power of Habit&lt;/a&gt;” by Charles Duhigg, I realized that there might be a better way: Habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habits are basically what the brain uses to conserve (mental) energy. The “autopilot” part of the brain. And for me, this was an awesome value proposition: When I set up the right habit, my brain would remind myself of the desired behaviour all by itself. Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-do-habits-work&quot;&gt;How do habits work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Duhigg explains that the “habit loop” has three major parts: a “cue” (or “trigger”), the behaviour itself, and a reward. Let’s have a quick look at the elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cue/Trigger: This basically the start button for the habit. When our brain recognizes the trigger (after the habit is established), it will then start to execute the behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Behaviour: These are the thoughts and actions that the brain executes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reward: A positive emotion that signals “hey this was good” to the brain. It is the incentive for our brain to remember the trigger and the behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the-habit-loop.png&quot; alt=&quot;Habit Loop&quot; style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Habit Loop is one of the core mechanism that our brain has used to learn for thousands of years. It requires no effort. In a nutshell, every time you feel a positive emotion, the brain asks itself: What was the environment like (cue/trigger) before or during the behaviour? What have I done (behaviour) before I felt the positive emotion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the brain tries to figure out: When (cue) and I do (behaviour) then I get (reward). And after it has figured this out, the brain tries to improve the odds of getting the reward: it executes the behaviour when it recognizes the trigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is: When you harness the power of this mechanism, you can help yourself to execute behaviours that are good for you more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the next post, I’ll go into more details regarding the nuts and bolts of what you have to do to harness the power of Habits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Habits are a basic building block of human behaviour. If you want to change your behaviour, then understanding habits is one of the best investments you can make. Read the post to get the 3 minute management summary.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/the-habit-loog.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Easy eats Courage for Breakfast</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/easy-eats-courage-for-breakfast" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Easy eats Courage for Breakfast" /><published>2018-05-28T05:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-28T05:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/easy-eats-courage-for-breakfast</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/easy-eats-courage-for-breakfast">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/success-small.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Success&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I have received feedback on my blog posts.  One aspect of the feedback was “I would also like to start publishing, but I do not dare to share my work. You know, I am not as courageous as you are and cannot write such personal things…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which actually left me eyes-wide-open astonished. Not because I had only 3 blog posts with about 600 words in total. But because I do not think that &lt;strong&gt;courage has had anything to do with it.&lt;/strong&gt; And I think: &lt;strong&gt;everyone can do that.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come back with me one week and you will hopefully understand why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-warp-one-week-back&quot;&gt;Time warp one week back…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a week ago, my inner dialogue was something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I start publishing, I want the result to be awesome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;because I do not want other people to think ‘oh, no, not another one of those amateur blogs’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that as a foundation, I would go on to tell myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;but I do not really have something awesome to write about - why should somebody else care about my thoughts…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and writing in an awesome way requires that I spend a lot of time and work on it - am I really sure I want to do that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I would think “oh, this is too hard”. It felt like this &lt;strong&gt;HUGE TASK&lt;/strong&gt;. It scared me. I did not think I had a good chance of being successful. And therefore, I did not start to write. And then I felt bad, and because I somehow knew that publishing was important to me and that I did not know how to accomplish my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can believe me when I say that &lt;strong&gt;courageous&lt;/strong&gt; was the last thing I felt at that point in time. Au contraire, mon ami. I felt I did not have courage because I did not do the &lt;strong&gt;scary HUGE TASK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-when-did-i-get-courageous&quot;&gt;So when did I get courageous?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a trick question. Because as I said above, I do not think that courage has had anything to do with it. I did not need courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something else was needed: The decision to shrink the &lt;strong&gt;scary HUGE TASK&lt;/strong&gt; into the &lt;strong&gt;easily doable thing&lt;/strong&gt;. I was able to change the success criteria in such a way that I was very confident I could achieve my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually I remember how thought: Well, that’s easy - I can do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-how-did-i-do-it&quot;&gt;And how did I do it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it started with giving myself the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/2GJv0ha&quot;&gt;permission to suck&lt;/a&gt;”. And it helped that I defined success as publishing only 100 words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now my inner dialogue looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most important thing is that I publish at least 100 words every workday&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I try my best to make those 100 words helpful to at least one person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I try to help by showing where I struggled and how I could make progress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I celebrate after publishing my 100+ words - because that’s the thing only I can control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new thought process puts me in the driver seat. I am in control to write 100 words and publish them. And I know when I tried to help one person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy now to feel successful. I mean, 100 words, come on, that’s basically a short email. And It can even be a sucky email. Why would I need courage for that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;everyone-can-do-that&quot;&gt;Everyone can do that&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that everybody can go from “the person that does not have the courage to publish” to “the person who thinks publishing is easy’ in a very short period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it took only a couple of hours work and 3 blog posts with about 600 words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic trick is: Make your objective smaller. So small you do not need courage any more. That’s how you can get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recommendation: Set up a new habit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every time you think&lt;/strong&gt; “I am afraid, I need more courage”,&lt;br /&gt;
stop yourself, and think  &lt;strong&gt;“Easy eats Courage for Breakfast”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and ask yourself &lt;strong&gt;“What could be an easy step that takes me into this direction?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I am not asking you to believe me. I am asking you to believe your own experience. Try this for a couple of days - and let me know how it works for you via Twitter or any other way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Waiting for courage in order to start can keep you waiting forever. Because courage does not come before doing. And it's faulty thinking that courage is required. Something else does the trick: making things easy.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/success-small.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Lay the Foundation for an Awesome Day</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/foundation-of-an-awesome-day" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Lay the Foundation for an Awesome Day" /><published>2018-05-25T03:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-25T03:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/foundation-of-an-awesome-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/foundation-of-an-awesome-day">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/maui.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Maui Landscape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my last posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/2GJv0ha&quot;&gt;habit formation&lt;/a&gt;, I have mentioned the Stanford University psychologist BJ Fogg. Another gold nugget I have gotten from him is his suggestion for an early morning habit that can lay the foundation for an awesome day. He calls it the MauiHabit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suggestion is to create the following habit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When&lt;/strong&gt; I get out of my bed, and &lt;strong&gt;my feet touch the ground,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
I will &lt;strong&gt;say to myself ‘Today is going to be an awesome day’.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I can understand if you think “Really? That’s it?”. I would have thought the same. But: I have tried his suggestion for the last couple of days: I was easy to do, it has put a smile on my face. That for itself could be enough, but on top of that, I have had a couple of awesome days this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I am not asking you to believe me. I am asking you to believe your own experience. Try this for a couple of days - and let me know how it works for you via Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In my last posts on habit formation, I have mentioned the Stanford University psychologist BJ Fogg. Another gold nugget I have gotten from him is his suggestion for an early morning habit that can lay the foundation for an awesome day. He calls it the MauiHabit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/images/maui.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">100 words on … making habit formation more successful</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/making-habit-formation-more-successful" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 words on … making habit formation more successful" /><published>2018-05-24T03:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T03:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/100-words-on-raising-the-bar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/making-habit-formation-more-successful">&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I was talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/2GJv0ha&quot;&gt;making it easy to start&lt;/a&gt;: By making it so simple you cannot fail — and giving yourself permission to suck because it is highly likely that you will do so in the beginning. For me, the bar is currently: Publish 100 words every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One feedback I have received was: “Great, now that you have done 100 words — set the bar to 200 tomorrow.” But I am not going to raise the bar. At least not for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is based on BJ Foggs recommendation: &lt;strong&gt;“Easy” is key for establishing new habits&lt;/strong&gt;. Part of my objective is to set up a habit where I do this regularly. And to establish a behavior as a habit, it is necessary to do the behavior in the first place — and then be able to feel a sense of accomplishment after I have done the desired behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about publishing 100 words now, I immediately get the feeling: I can do this. That’s easy. Which actually makes me want to do the publishing, because I know I will feel great afterwards. On the other hand, if I would raise the bar, I felt myself unsure if I reach my goal — and as a consequence I was not as motivated to get started in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I will keep the bar at 100 words for now. And maybe raise the bar when I get to the point where I think “100 words is too boring”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d be interested if you have made a similar experience. Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In the last post, I was talking about making it easy to start: By making it so simple you cannot fail — and giving yourself permission to suck because it is highly likely that you will do so in the beginning. For me, the bar is currently: Publish 100 words every day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 words on … overcoming resistance to start publishing</title><link href="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/overcoming-resistance-to-start" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 words on … overcoming resistance to start publishing" /><published>2018-05-23T03:42:39-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-23T03:42:39-05:00</updated><id>http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/100-words-on-overcoming-resistance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.happy-and-productive.com/overcoming-resistance-to-start">&lt;p&gt;I have been struggling with my objective to start publishing content on the Internet now for a while. I’ve tried a lot of things: Setting up habits to write every morning, reading a lot on how to do things. But in the end, I have not been able to establish something regular, much less publish ANYTHING.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I have listened to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/il-2a1UYb0&quot;&gt;podcast with BJ Fogg and David Kadavy&lt;/a&gt;: They were talking about how to make it &lt;strong&gt;simple enough&lt;/strong&gt; to just do it. And David said that he gave himself &lt;strong&gt;permission to suck&lt;/strong&gt;. So, I am resetting my bar to just publish 100 words for now. Without any wanting it to be great, awesome, new, innovative, value-adding. Just starting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because it is the only way to learn and get better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have been struggling with my objective to start publishing content on the Internet now for a while. I’ve tried a lot of things: Setting up habits to write every morning, reading a lot on how to do things. But in the end, I have not been able to establish something regular, much less publish ANYTHING.</summary></entry></feed>